so our next speaker has requested I
introduce him as a professor in exile
from Evergreen State College down in
Washington State so please give a warm
welcome for dr. Brett Weinstein hi there
thank you for that nice warm welcome
it's great to see so many people who as
I understand it are gathered because
they are interested in Liberty I must
say I also am quite interested in
Liberty so I'm looking forward to
talking to many of you and to the panel
discussion that will come later I should
say I had some jokes that I was going to
open up with but somebody warned me that
I should not make jokes about hockey
while in Canada so there goes the first
15 minutes of what I was planning to say
you can learn a lot from what people
tell you you're not allowed to joke
about in a particular location my wife
and I went on our honeymoon in Turkey
and we were told that Turks are very
warm people who will talk to you about
just about anything but don't joke about
Ataturk so Ataturk if you're in Turkey
hockey if you're in Canada these are
topics to be treated carefully all right
so um yeah the title of my talk is how
the magic trick is done I have a very
odd position at the moment and that
position is as somebody who is
analytically fascinated by systems and
the way they evolve and at the same time
I'm at the center of an event that
presumably many of you know about at
Evergreen State College so I've had the
opportunity to watch this system evolve
from a vantage point that few people
have and it means that my analytical
side has been tracking the way such
movements function and has been learning
an amazing amount at a tremendous rate
just by virtue of the fact that there's
so much to
scene and to be discussed alternative
title for the talk that I rejected is
evergreen is your future because as much
as I think what happened at Evergreen is
extraordinary I do think what it is is
ahead of the curve and if we're not
careful what happened at Evergreen is
going to happen everywhere and we really
ought to be careful because as much as
what took place at Evergreen was absurd
and therefore in some ways potentially
amusing if you weren't trapped in it
what it represents is actually quite
dangerous and I don't just mean
dangerous even to the university system
which would be bad enough but really
dangerous to civilization itself because
the university system is where those who
run civilization figure out how to think
and if we take the the mechanisms
whereby we train people how to think
critically and carefully and how to
discover things that are true that they
don't they don't expect or into it then
civilization is going to lose its
ability to navigate and I must say I
find that prospect absolutely
frightening so my plan is to talk a
little bit about some observations some
of these observations have a particular
place in a kind of a logical progression
other ones stand isolated but
nonetheless I think it's worth your time
to have heard them from what I guess is
an insider perspective so you can
recognize them when they happen in other
places so let's talk a little bit about
humor we brushed on that topic a little
bit to begin with but there's something
that is decidedly humorless about the
social justice warrior culture and I
must say when I find people are
humorless it doesn't necessarily tell me
that they're bad but it does send up a
warning flag and the reason for that is
because humor has a very special role to
play for human civilization we navigate
gray area nuance the counterintuitive
that which is not what it seems all of
those things are navigated normally
humor it's a way in which we can tread
into that territory without committing
ourselves fully but investigating what's
actually true so a humorless movement is
in some sense a mobile it cannot be
convinced that it has something wrong
and it cannot redirect itself and so
when we look at the social justice
revolution and we find it very committed
to things that are not even superficial
superficially reasonable part of what
must have happened is its own commitment
to the idea that what it already
believes is sufficiently true that it
does not need to redirect in any way
that commitment has kept it on a steady
bearing that cannot be disrupted next
thing to say is that some stories
diagnose a system and so the story of
what happened at Evergreen happens to
have diagnosed several systems some of
which we are all involved in it
certainly diagnosed the press in a way
that I find most disturbing so let's for
the moment be overly overly
black-and-white about it and
dichotomized the press into the
nominally left-leaning and the nominally
right leaning press the left-leaning
press with some significant exceptions
came very late to the story and was very
reluctant about reporting it to their to
the extent it was willing to report it
at all now why is that so well I'm
afraid the answer is the story did not
fit the left narrative in fact it said
there was something wrong with the
standard left narrative that needed to
be understood and so the left press
rather than figure out how to report the
story decided it would rather not report
the story and maybe just wait it out see
if the story would go away now if I can
just be clear about what the problem was
at Evergreen we had bigots of color even
worse we had black bigots of color that
is not a comfortable story for the left
it's a story the left does not like it's
a story I do not like nonetheless that
what happened and therefore if you were
to approach the Evergreen story
journalistically you would be compelled
to figure out how to report that story
and to the extent that it reflected
badly on the left narrative so be it but
that wasn't the way the press works now
in part we could say shame on the press
but we could also say well why is the
press reluctant to report
counterintuitive stories for one thing
you would imagine that that would draw a
certain number of people to read a
counterintuitive story Man Bites Dog is
more interesting than than dog bites man
right so you might imagine that there
would be some draw for the left press to
report a story that doesn't sound like
normal on the other hand in a market the
press has to compete long term against
other elements of the press and one of
the things that the press like other
entities do is it tells us things that
reinforce the beliefs we already hold in
order to get us to come back and so
there is some reflex there to simply
reject a story in which the bigots are
black the right-leaning press did
something different
the right-leaning press engaged in
regular journalism now I don't mean
every entity on the right but I do mean
in general there were a number of
publications that are decidedly
right-of-center that reported the story
perfectly straight now
you can't necessarily know that as
outsiders to the story but as somebody
who knew the players of the story could
spot every error that was reported every
time the press said something that was
factually incorrect it was obvious to me
and to my wife who was also a professor
at Evergreen and it was not necessarily
obvious to the public so I can tell you
which press outlets did the best job
which ones did their homework which ones
figured out who was who and what their
roles were and campus reform did a great
job the Weekly Standard did a great job
The Wall Street Journal did a great job
so what I'm telling you is that in this
particular case there was an outbreak of
great journalism on the right because
the story didn't conflict with anything
that forced the right leading press into
a contortion
now I don't think either right or left
really has the answer at the moment I
think both right and left are a bit
confused and they're confused about
different things but this story says
something about the press and it's
polarization and what its implications
are for society the core issue is one of
narrative there are narratives that run
underneath what the press reports either
right or left and to the extent that a
story violates the core narrative it's a
problem to the extent that it validates
a core narrative it is seen as positive
what we as consumers of journalism
should be thinking is there's a problem
that the press is built around
narratives and that it is doing any kind
of analysis whatsoever that depends on a
particular story of matching a narrative
what we should want is a press that is
non ideological and reports the story as
it is and to the extent that it
validates some narrative in the outer
world so be it but narrative should not
be driving our journalism and yet the
diagnosis of the system here is that
narrative is playing a profound role in
everything but you can only see it when
something causes an error another system
that was diagnosed by this fiasco is the
university system the university system
has been engaged in multiple jobs in
society it certainly plays an important
role in training people to function but
it's also involved in industry and it's
involved in markets and it is involved
in politics and all of these things have
caused universities to act in a way that
is counterproductive to the cause of
inquiry and that should probably be our
primary take-home message here is that
inquiry is essential and it cannot start
if you know your conclusions inquiry
honest inquiry is generated when you are
willing to discover that your
conclusions are dead wrong the legal
system also showed itself in this case
my wife and I we did not actually reach
the point of filing suit against our
College because there is a 60-day
waiting period and we settled with the
college before filing suit but
the less we did get to experience the
attorney general's office and we
discovered that there is actually a
hazard in this social justice movement
that is moving through our legal system
as well so to the extent that there are
significant penalties to be paid by
people who espouse heterodox
perspectives that has strong
implications for what it would look like
to to impanel a jury what are the
chances that you're going to get 12
people who are open-minded enough to be
able to deal with a story that for
example the New York Times fumbled I
should probably say the New York Times
fumbled the story in an interesting way
the op-ed page did a pretty good job
Barry Weiss and Frank Bruni both wrote
excellent op eds on the evergreen story
that told the story pretty straight and
then the news division waited for weeks
and it told a very comforting story for
its readers that was quite at odds with
the reality of what had happened I find
myself in a unique and I hesitate to use
the word privileged position as a result
of what's happened I have paid the price
to be able to tell it straight they
challenged me they called me a racist it
turned out that stigma didn't stick in
my case I happen to be lucky enough to
have a large number of people who knew
it wasn't true and there were enough
elements in my past that said that
simply doesn't add up that I survived
that attack having survived that attack
I can now just simply speak freely and
one question I want you to ask
yourselves is what do we do about the
fact that most people aren't lucky
enough to have a history that tells that
story clearly they are in a worse
position from the point of view of
defending themselves and what we really
ought to be thinking is how are we going
to arrange to make it safe for people to
engage in honest inquiry and discussion
alright now to some deeper analysis the
first thing to understand about what we
are facing is that it sounds like a
bunch of arguments about what is factual
true it's very confusing though because
these arguments aren't even
superficially defensible so how can
people be making arguments that are so
clearly wrong and yet be surviving in
the marketplace of ideas well they're
not really arguments what we face is an
insurgency the insurgency is behaving
tactically not analytically so the
arguments aren't for real now to be sure
there are arguments being made but they
are largely being made behind closed
doors amongst participants in the
insurgency and then what we see on the
outside are basically a PR campaign
designed to have certain effects but not
not built around deeply held beliefs so
that's very confusing until you spot
that that's what you're up against then
when you see it you can start to realize
that the arguments being leveled at you
can't be answered because there's
nothing you could possibly say that
would cause those listening to you to
pivot how do we know this well first of
all a lot is said online if you know
where to look so you will find people
within the movement describing their
relative roles and explaining why it is
that certain people should behave this
way in that way and if you listen in you
can figure out what the rules of the
game are but you can also spot that
there is a system of things that if one
accepts them cannot be escaped so for
example there are linguistic traps and
there are many of them so a linguistic
trap involves something like the
redefinition of a word like racism or
white supremacy so the word gets
redefined and it gets redefined in a way
that sets the bar incredibly low so that
really you can't help a trip over it
having tripped over it the penalty phase
takes the definition right back to its
traditional one so if you turn out to be
a white supremacist because you have
failed to properly confront a system
that has been deemed guilty of white
supremacy then the penalty for white
supremacy is as if you have burned a
cross on someone's long right that is
unfair and lot
ethically inconsistent but nonetheless
very effective nobody wants to be
declared a white supremacist there are
many of these traps and they are
distributed around the landscape such
that if you try to just simply navigate
by intuition you can't help but run
afoul of them the other thing that
you'll find are Trojan horse proposals
so these are policy proposals that
superficially seem all right but the
details of them which are a little bit
often hard to ferret out are very
dangerous so evergreens meltdown
surrounded something called the
strategic equity plan now the strategic
equity plan was I will never know for
sure if it was intentional but it was
written in such a dull fashion such a
dry manner that nobody could possibly
want to read it you really had to force
herself to take your medicine but having
read it it included all kinds of plans
to restructure the college that were not
only unfair and unwise but put the
college in danger of fiscal insolvency
what I really got in trouble for was not
the day of absence and my objection to
it what I really got in trouble for was
my opposition to the strategic equity
proposal on the basis that it wasn't a
smart thing for the college to sign up
for that was unforgivable and it caused
a number of people to believe that I
needed to be driven out of the college
otherwise I was going to be the lone
obstacle to that proposal mind you most
of the people pushing that proposal have
not read it I guarantee you that I think
many of the people whose names are on it
had not read it the number of errors in
the document when it was first released
was so great that it is impossible that
all of those people had gone through it
and not spotted them for one thing all
right
the arguments are not real there are
linguistic traps
there are Trojan horse proposals and
there is a great deal of leverage being
wielded by driving ones costs so that is
to say there is a system of making you
pay a high penalty if you do something
like challenge the strategic equity
proposal
in public driving ones cost does not
necessarily require you to be guilty of
anything it can be done in many
different ways and it is something to
pay attention to it is a hallmark of a
conscious strategic actor that they will
drive your costs up in order to
disincentivize you're saying things that
they don't really care if you believe
they just don't want you voicing them
they don't want these objections to
spread all right the insurgency cheats
it reworks the world to avail itself of
tools that we reserved for self-defense
so when I say self-defense some circuit
in your mind goes off because you know
that if you are defending yourselves
you're entitled to do things that you
would not under ordinary circumstances
be entitled to do you cannot kill
somebody unless you are acting in
self-defense and then you absolutely can
and you'll walk away scot-free
so self-defense is a very powerful
concept if you are engaged in
self-defense you are entitled to do
things that you are not allowed to do
otherwise much of the language
surrounding the social justice
revolution is phrased in terms of
self-defense
they say that speech is violence well
who is it violence against well it's
violence against those who are
historically oppressed what does it mean
well it means they are entitled to avail
themselves of tools that they would not
otherwise be allowed to utilize right
that's a simple sleight of hand by
causing speech to be violence you avail
yourself of violent tools in response
very often
that's what the anti-shah is doing right
they're engaged in actual physical
violence against people espousing what
are sometimes bad ideas but not always
okay
it also it labels people to delegitimize
them so I've met many interesting
characters since May when things melted
down at Evergreen one thing I've met
that great many of our people who
believe themselves to be progressive and
on the left but have been described
publicly as on the right now this has
happened to me so I know
it's funny right the idea that I'm on
the right is preposterous because I am a
lifelong progressive and my position on
this hasn't changed as a result of my
experiences at Evergreen now that said
many of the policy proposals that the
left favors I am skeptical of but
nonetheless my values if we were to sit
down and talk about it you'd discover
that I am indeed a a true progressive
but these other folks I've met I very
often encountered them online before I
meet them in person I met the folks from
spiked online the other day their
Wikipedia page describes them as
libertarian I mentioned this to them and
they they bridled at this description
they said don't read the Wikipedia page
it gets us all wrong were actually
progressives and they went into their
bona fides so many of the people are now
orphaned effectively by being shoved out
of the left nominally and into some kind
of no-man's land
all right they are deemed to be right or
if you do something that really annoys
people you will be deemed to be all
right and the threshold for being all
right is a bar that again has been set
so low you couldn't help but but trip
over it so for example one of the
favorite tropes of people in the social
justice movement is to declare you all
right because somebody made an all-right
comment under a YouTube video you posted
and you didn't delete it all right
that's a heck of a standard but
nonetheless I've seen it happen multiple
times we had the group patriot prayer
come to Evergreen actually oddly they
came to defend my free speech rights
they were described by faculty members
as Nazis from Portland that was the
literal description of them this
description makes little sense I'm
Jewish
Nazis unless they were deeply confused
to be unlikely to come defend my free
speech rights but nonetheless these
folks came and they gave some speeches
outside the campus and my wife and I
watched them live streamed the speech
was conspicuous also inconsistent with
being a Nazi
they were extremely tolerant of people
from different racial groups they
espoused tolerance for trans people for
gay people they seem to be very much in
favor of free expression none of this
made any sense weeks later when patriot
prayer showed up in Berkeley and were
attacked again by the anti feh the
Weekly Standard ran an expose on Patriot
Prayer and it turned out the Patriot
Prayer was headed by a guy who is
actually half Japanese his right-hand
man is Samoan these people aren't
remotely racist they are interested in
tolerance they are Trump supporters it's
true but lukewarm on him in other words
the whole idea that they were not to use
from Portland was cooked up to dismiss
them so that nobody would listen to them
that was the idea and it didn't matter
that they were slandered in the process
all right there are two kinds of people
within the social justice movement you
can't necessarily tell them apart
because the current system their current
circumstances make them sound alike
the first group by far the much larger
group and the much more difficult one
for people like me to figure out what to
do with our people who are actually
against oppression I am against
oppression so ordinarily I would think
these would be my natural allies but yet
they attack me the second group inside
the movement are people who wish to turn
the tables of oppression those would be
my enemies the fact is though the ones
who wish to confront oppression and to
undo it don't realize what they have
signed up for many of the prime movers
in the movement are actually bad actors
who have not shared the plan with the
rank-and-file of the movement so many of
the people inside the movement are
well-intentioned but not skeptical
enough and have fallen into something
unholy the allies tend to sign on based
on what I would call the label on the
box so there's a box
it says equity on it and then people are
asked well are you in favor of racial
equity most people would answer yes okay
you're with us but what's in the box is
not actually equity and so one finds if
you sign up based on the label of the
box if you've signed up for something
that you didn't bargain for there's
another reason that allies sign on with
the bad actors who are driving the
social justice movement and that is out
of fear of being targeted themselves so
we have a very dangerous movement it's
proven that it has the power to harm
people and many people who fear that it
might come for them that it might ferret
out some kind of hidden white supremacy
in their minds or something sign up in
an effort to demonstrate that they are
good people so that the movement does
not come after them we also have what I
would call marginal coalition members
who have signed up in in an effort to
get ahead for fear that they will be
shunted on to the other side so the
Coalition is built from
intersectionality a term you've no doubt
all heard where one's rank within some
sort of future idealized state is based
on how much historical oppression you
have faced based on which populations
you belong to and what their history has
been now I will point out that even if
we accept intersectionality on its own
terms
it is completely incoherent so for
example as a Jewish person in the United
States I have not experienced too much
oppression myself that said if
intersectionality is good to its word
than the fact that my ancestors
experienced literally thousands of years
of consistent oppression ought to count
in my favor with respect to whether or
not I have the right to an opinion
whether I have the right to help shape
the movement but now in fact for some
reason my Judaism counts against me I
can't fathom why except for the fact
that really it's a self-serving ideology
that
chooses to highlight certain facts and
to de-emphasize others so coalition
members are prioritized based on how
many different categories of historical
oppression they can claim apply to them
which means that there are a certain
number of groups that have only a small
number of these oppression points on our
campus people who are simply gay have
only one oppression point and so they
have to work extra hard in order to
remain in the good graces of the
movement the same thing goes for people
who are simply women also Asians now I'm
not making this up and I'm not even
inferring it the fact is during the day
of absence there were seminars on how a
Shannara of the problem when it comes to
white supremacy you can't even really
make this stuff up
it's that preposterous so in any way in
any case my point would be you can
imagine if you have some dangerous force
wielding the power over your ability to
do your job or to be hired or the
likelihood that you will be fired if
that group is wielding that kind of
power and you happen to be on the border
of its good graces some fraction of
people will choose to behave in a way
that advertises that they are signed up
for this plan whatever it is in hopes of
just simply getting out of the way of it
universities and colleges are now at the
epicenter of this fight many of us who
have been involved deeply in making
University and college culture find this
very odd is it really true that we have
a terrible problem with racism on
college campuses today is that really
what we're to infer from this I think
it's very much the wrong conclusion
what's happening is there are deep
problems with equality and they're very
uncomfortable to navigate but the
colleges and universities are being
attacked not because they are the
epicenter of this in fact they are the
most progressive places that we have
they are the places that are most likely
to recognize
Oracle oppression and to realize that it
has important implications for how well
people do in life but what they are is
soft targets they're soft targets and
because they're listening they are easy
to manipulate were it the objective of
this social justice movement to confront
the much more difficult problems and to
confront them at the full level of
nuance I would be interested in seeing
those problems addressed but I cannot
sign up with a movement that is
attacking those people who have come the
greatest distance toward creating an
equitable situation okay so what is it
that this movement is actually trying to
achieve now remember I'm arguing that
they're actually two groups embedded in
one movement one of those groups is
really hoping to achieve some kind of
equality hopefully they're pursuing
equality of opportunity not equality of
result but nonetheless equality is
something I would guess everybody in the
room here would sign up for as an ideal
that would be worth pursuing but then
there's the other faction the faction
that I'm arguing is actually driving the
agenda of the movement what do they want
well it's very uncomfortable and in fact
I got into big trouble for tweeting that
the movement at Evergreen was actually
involved in achieving black supremacy
now it's interesting I must have been
challenged 20 times over having used the
term black supremacy not once did
anybody tell me that that was not what
they had seen unfolding during the
protest at Evergreen they told me
effectively that that was an impolite
term for it but we had all seen it we
had all seen the circumstance where
people would walk into a room and they
would say the food the chairs the water
that's not for white people if you're a
white person's stand in the back don't
sit in the chairs don't eat the food
this was actually said out loud
so in some sense it's undeniable that
what was being pursued was a kind of
supremacy
my feeling is I'm against any kind of
suppress
see I would like to see everybody have
access to the means to get ahead through
achievement I don't want to see any
population advantaged in any population
disadvantaged so I'm anti supremacy and
that means that I have to be offended if
I'm to be consistent with that principle
I have to be offended when any
population seeks supremacy over
everybody else nonetheless we find
ourselves trapped in a situation where
we can't even use the terms that
naturally apply what they've advocated
on a narrow a more narrow level is if we
were to analyze it honestly it is a
program of radical reparations and when
I say radical reparations reparations is
a controversial concept I can't say that
I'm even necessarily against it if it
were wisely done although I'm pretty
sure that simple payments are not a good
idea but nonetheless I can imagine a
good argument for the idea that some
populations have been systematically
disadvantaged and that the correct
remedy for that is to provide some kind
of help systematic help now if it were
me writing the script I would say
investment in those communities would be
the right way to go but nonetheless
reasonable people can disagree over what
the right way to view a reparations
argument is I don't think reasonable
people can disagree over the following
question is it okay to set up a
reparations program in your classroom
right are you allowed to transfer the
educational well-being of one group of
your students to another group of your
students I can't see a reasonable
argument for that and yet I know that
that is what is unfolding in classrooms
today on the basis that it is clearly
the right thing from some people's
perspective the so-called progressive
stack in which students are called upon
in reverse order of their historical
privilege is preposterous for one thing
you know nothing about the individual
histories of the students there I've had
white students who have spent years
eating roadkill because their families
didn't have
to eat that student is not somehow so
emboldened by a history of privilege
that they should wait to ask their
question questions should be asked by
people who have them and any professor
who sidelines students because they're
black or they're gay is a problem any
professor who's sideline students
because they're white is a problem this
is just simply what real equity would
look like but nonetheless we are
effectively told that within
institutions and within classrooms that
effectively a forced unacknowledged
campaign of reparations is the right
solution so critical race theory is the
intellectual home of much of the
foundation of the social justice
movement critical race theory is where
intersectionality emerged from but it
has become something of a con game it
has become a place that one can justify
illogical things and then move them into
the policy layer without having to
explain oneself my brother Eric
Weinstein has coined the phrase the
intersectional shakedown that
effectively people are being relieved of
their well being on the basis that
there's some justification for doing so
and it's not only it is simply immoral
and we have to confront it many players
that you will find signed up for the
current social justice agenda are
actually involved in the racket as free
agents they are serving their own
interests at public expense and this
this is actually something that one
would predict if one were well schooled
in something called game theory now I
must say I'm a huge fan of game theory
I'm an evolutionary biologist and so
game theory is at the core of what I
think about all the time but I must say
if there's one subject that I think
people would
benefit greatly from studying if if you
wanted to add something to the list of
things that you were looking into game
theory would be at the top of the list
when I say game theory to people though
I very often get a strange reaction it
has some kind of a bad stigma associated
with it and I think what goes on is the
term game is confusing to people when
you when you hear about people's
problems in civilization and you say
well this is really a question of game
theory it sounds like you're
trivializing the issue so we need to get
we either need to rename game theory or
get over that stigma and realize that
game theory the meaning of the term game
in the situation is that this is about
complex systems in which there is
competition in which there is winning
and losing and it describes all such
systems it describes living biological
systems
it describes economic systems it
describes political systems and
therefore is at the core of all of these
things that we're trying to sort out and
understanding the game theory of the
social justice movement is I think
essential if we are going to if we are
going to defeat it so there are three
kinds of players in the movement and
they are motivated to be there by three
different things there are the prime
movers which I described already the
prime movers are people who are actually
advancing their own agenda and are most
likely to be conscious of what they are
doing they get ahead through
manipulation presumably they are the
source of many of the linguistic traps
and the policy proposals and the cost
driving that allows the movement to
function the second group of people
after the prime movers are the tools so
the tools in the movement are people who
have signed up maybe because they've
heard a sound bite about what sorts of
values they are pursuing and they
haven't looked any more deeply into it
and they find themselves being bossed
around and told how to serve the
movement best we saw a lot of this at
Evergreen many of the people who were
fighting for
a sort of intersectional reversal of
historical a prep oppression were
themselves white students now you can
understand this more deeply if you look
into their own discussions about ally
shape so we've all heard about ally ship
and probably many of us in this room
have a sort of a conflict within
ourselves when we hear that term I know
that I certainly did I regard myself as
an ally of people who have been
historically oppressed it seems to me
that that's the right thing to be to
understand that historical oppression
has an implication in the present and
that it it carries obligations on the
other hand in order to be an ally within
the movement one has to sign up for
certain things that I was never going to
sign up for and probably most of you
wouldn't either
so what are those things well Ally is
one of these terms that's been redefined
Ally if we speak in common parlance is a
term that connotes a symmetrical peer
relationship to nations Ally with each
other that doesn't put one in charge of
the other it means that they're teaming
up for some sort of a common goal that's
not how it is inside this movement
inside the movement Ally ship is very
definitely a subordinate relationship
I'm told that many of the students who
came to protests me at my classroom I
knew none of these students by the way
all of the students who showed up were
brand new to me many of them apparently
showed up not knowing why they were
there to protest they were told it was
their obligation to the movement and
that they should show up and they were
given a piece of paper that described
things they were supposed to say and I
will say many of them I think were
confounded by actually talking to me
because I wasn't the cartoon that they
had been told I was I'm an anti-racist
and they thought they were confronting a
racist and that was initially confusing
to them and when they discovered that
little paradox what happened is they
went into a very automatic mode rather
than come back and tell whoever had
instructed them to show
my class hey I think he got something
wrong because that guy didn't sound like
you told us he was gonna sound they went
into some mode where they started
chanting and they started reading from
this piece of paper rather than have to
confront was that what was actually in
front of them so it is the subordinate
relationship and in fact it gets even
worse than subordinate there is a
discussion I ran into online in which
there was a very explicit equivalency
made between a lie ship and being an
accomplice the idea was that inherent to
the job of the social justice movement
was breaking the rules and breaking the
law and that if you were really
committed to the values that the
movement claims to be advancing that
your obligation if you were not
historically oppressed was to break the
law for them that was the idea a lie is
an accomplice and it is an accomplice
that does what they're told is
subordinate accomplice so I'm not
exaggerating when I call these people
tools that's what they've become that's
what they've allowed themselves to
become okay the third group the first
two were the prime movers and the tools
the third group are the free agents so
these are people who are really
opportunists they don't need to sign up
for this stuff but they get ahead by
doing so and some of them are perfectly
cynical some of them may be self-deluded
but there are many different types at
Evergreen we had administrators
administrators who find themselves
getting ahead by signing up for this
muscular movement within the faculty and
the students to challenge them might be
costly to one's career but to simply
sign up and advance their cause leaves
you as an administrator much less likely
to be targeted so there's a duality to
the role because on the one hand the
social justice movement structures
itself so that administrators will make
this choice and the administrators do so
because many administrators are in fact
cynical self promoting people and so
it's affect it's effectively a
partnership between two cynical entities
you'll also find this amongst podcasters
and and journalists so these people by
writing stories that flatter this
viewpoint get a ready-made readership or
listenership and if your well being as a
podcaster or a journalist comes from the
fact that you've got a lot of eyes on
your pieces then standing out as
somebody who is who is advancing this
particular cause is a way to get ahead
and so they do it and professors too
especially at Evergreen there were a
number of professors who took a lead in
defending the strategic equity proposal
who were initially its target so they
were initially its target and then they
switched and they became aggressive
advocates and then they became allies to
this movement which I think these
professors had identified as likely to
win and if this movement wins and it
advances its professors into powerful
roles on hiring committees and it
advances its proposals through the
faculty governance structure then those
people who have been strong advocates
during the process of ascent are likely
to be brought along with it whereas if
you're challenged you're liable to fall
by the wayside okay so that gives you
some sense of who the players are now I
want to talk a little bit about the
system that they bring along with them I
call it a hermetically sealed system and
you will probably those of you who have
faced these arguments will have
encountered the frustration of trying to
challenge them logically and not being
able to make any headway at all and what
I submit to you is that the reason she
can't make headway is that there's
essentially a flowchart in which every
single argument you could conceivably
make has been mapped and if you make a
new argument then the closest thing on
the map will be assumed to be the
argument that you've made and you will
be shunted to the proper response to
shut it down right there is no defeating
this thing and it's composed of several
different kinds of components so the
first one is bad assumption
there are bad assumptions that if you
don't look at them to carefully might
sound like they have some truth in them
but if you scrutinize them you'll
discover they don't but once you've
accepted them what they cause you to
conclude is some radically bizarre
upside-down universe so here are some
examples lived experience Trump's
population analysis right so population
level analysis is what we would
typically do in a scientific study we
would look at some sort of pattern and
we'd say is this pattern the result of
some cause like for example bias that
exists inside the system well if you
take the assumption that lived
experience is actually the only valid
thing and that population level analysis
is somehow incapable of recovering what
it is that takes place in people's lives
well then you will discover that all
sorts of people have stories to tell
about oppression that they've faced
which might well not stand up if it were
scrutinized in some sort of rigorous
dispassionate way so to give you a
trivial example you know if let's say a
woman is walking down the street and all
right let's make this person let's say a
woman is walking down the street and I
am walking down the street in the other
direction and I look at her in a way
that she finds uncomfortable well she
may have the sense that I have had some
ill intent now if she doesn't know that
I've looked at the guy who followed her
in exactly the same way she is incapable
of calibrating her experience it's no
failing of hers it's just a failing of
the anecdote she's had one experience
but she has no idea maybe I'm a guy who
gives people awkward looks right maybe
it has nothing to do with her being
female at all but she's not in a
position to know that because she's had
one experience so this is why in fact
scientific analysis looks the way it
does because we are well aware that
things can look very much like something
but when you analyze at a population
level you may discover that the cause is
something very different also I would
point out that if you really do believe
as I do that there
our structural biases in our system that
are important and have major
consequences the way to establish that
is with a a dispassionate analysis at
the level of populations where you can
see that there is a real consequence of
some sort of process so signing up for
this bad assumption that lived
experience is the only true insight is a
terrible error on the other hand you can
imagine that it is very empowering if
you find yourself in a group that is
historically oppressed and suddenly
you're able to assert this is what I
have experienced this is what it means
and this is what the natural remedy for
it must be alright here's another one of
these assumptions reasonable people
cannot disagree now they don't say this
out loud but this is certainly the
implication of many things that they do
say so when you have the experience of
making arguments and they have no impact
on what's coming back from the other
side the point is the other side has
already reached a conclusion and it
believes that conclusion to have be
effectively perfect and anybody who
disagrees is disagreeing for some
illegitimate reason maybe the person on
the other side is cynical or there's
some sort of conspiracy afoot or
something like that and I would point
out reasonable people disagreeing is an
essential way for civilization to
function and that in fact this is a core
biological feature of human beings the
way we all end up in civilization is
that our ancestors figured out some
pretty difficult problems and they did
it by disagreeing with each other
disagreeing in good faith so that they
could discover what the real truth was
another bad assumption is that inquiry
itself is a bad thing now I was shocked
by this I did not see this one coming as
a scientist my feeling is that inquiry
is a beautiful thing and it reveals
truths that are profound and important
and have distinct implications for how
we should run civilization but during
the protests a student somebody I I
should tell you at Evergreen we teach
programs that are full time for both
professors and students so professors
know they're stood
much better than they would and
understand her circumstances student I
know very well somebody that my wife and
I on our study abroad program traveled
with in Ecuador for 11 weeks and spent a
year in a program with her student who
is half black was walking across our
campus she was walking to the science
buildings and she was confronted by
protesters who challenged her and
berated her for being black and studying
science now I must say I can't believe I
am standing at a podium telling that
story if I wake up in a half an hour and
it turns out this is a dream that will
be the most likely reason that I would
ever say such a thing into a microphone
the alternative is that it really
happened and that this is a real room
full of people who are assembled to hear
such stories it did happen
what we found out later my wife and I
was that this was not the only incident
that in fact many students of color had
been challenged for studying science at
Evergreen inquiry is bad if you were
involved in inquiry you are personally
bad you are betraying the values that
the social justice warriors are pushing
I find that offensive but nonetheless
it's a bad assumption on their list
meritocracy is some kind of trap so
meritocracy is something that they are
now challenging that meritocracy is a
trick that it is designed to reinforce
historical privilege and that we must
reject meritocracy effectively accepting
that what people do is inherently all of
equal quality this is obviously very
dangerous to a society that depends on
us innovating our way through puzzles
there's an assumption that one can
simply swap out the people at the front
of the room for other people and that it
will not have a negative consequence for
students so there is a campaign to hire
people that quote-unquote look like the
people in the room now if you think for
a moment about what a proposal on
campus to hire people that look like the
students in the room means it can't
possibly be mean anything if the room is
at all diverse you can't hire the person
that looks like the people in the chairs
but nonetheless there's a desire to hire
people at the front of the room who look
like the people in the chairs as if
hiring from a narrow population isn't
going to impact quality now I'm not
arguing that for example darker people
are lower quality scholars that's not
what I'm saying what I am saying is that
you want to hire from a large population
because you are looking for people who
have extraordinary capability and you
will find them they are in the tails of
the distribution if you hire from a
small population you won't see many
people in the tails of the distribution
so you won't be able to hire them but
nonetheless the social justice warriors
believe that it makes sense that it is a
worthy trade to simply change the skin
color of the people at the front of the
room to make people in the room more
comfortable the next bad assumption on
their list is that discomfort is its
self injury that if you are
uncomfortable you have been harmed and
therefore that there is a right to purge
uncomfortable things from the
educational landscape now this couldn't
possibly be more dangerous to the
education of the people in the classroom
if it tried discomfort is a sign that
something that you think is right is
being challenged now maybe it's being
challenged by something that is less
right than what you thought in which
case that discomfort will be temporary
and you will discover that your idea was
stronger than you thought it was and
your comfort will be restored or maybe
you're going to discover that your
discomfort is actually a sign that
something you thought was true is
actually false either way you come out
ahead so if we accept this assumption
and we borrow discomfort from the
classroom because it's a sign that we
are harming people then it is the death
of education that's really what it is
education involves discomforts used to
be openly said at Evergreen I haven't
heard it in a couple of years but it
used to be openly said that discomfort
was the key to educating people that
that was our job was to take people out
of their come
next assumption is that any time you
find yourself on the defensive your
opponent has pulled a fast one right so
there is an assumption that if somebody
says something that causes a member of
the social justice coalition to have to
think about what the answer might be
that that is inherently a sign of bad
faith action of some kind rather than a
sign that there's something to be
learned and finally a related point is
there is an assumption that when your
opponent makes gains there has been a
conspiracy now we have to deal with this
issue of conspiracy a little bit
carefully because it is one of those
third-rail issues that divides every
room but the fact is we all know
conspiracies happen there are real
conspiracies and we all know that many
allegations of conspiracy are false the
difficulty is that conspiracy is a
challenge to Occam's razor which is the
central principle to figuring out what
is true
conspiracies confound Occam's razor they
game Occam's razor but I now find myself
in a very funny position which is
because I have many friends left at
Evergreen on the faculty amongst the
students and on the staff I hear things
about what's taking place on the campus
there's currently a conspiracy theory
that involves me and why I was
successful at surviving their challenge
and I know it's false
I can't necessarily convince anybody
else of this but the very fact that I'm
in a position to say well actually that
conspiracy didn't happen and I'm one of
very few people who can say for sure
that that's the case it's a very
powerful position to be and nonetheless
to hear that conspiracy theory bubbling
through the campus as an explanation for
why they found themselves so embarrass
in the case of their protest against me
is fascinating so their assumption is if
you make gains against them you have
engaged in some kind of conspiracy okay
now these bad assumptions result in
conclusions that are themselves false
these conclusions are where the work
actually happens so the conclusions are
what allows them to wield power let me
give you some examples of some bad
conclusions one is if you oppose an
equity proposal then you are against
equity now this was a major trap at
Evergreen because there was a really bad
equity proposal in motion and if you
cared about the college you had to stand
up and say so and if you said so then it
was evidence of some major defect in
your character another bad conclusion is
that if you defend yourself against
accusations of racism you are evidencing
racism now this is a very clever little
trap which makes it impossible to know
how to react and the right thing to do
in the face of such a thing if you're
simply trying to stay alive is keep your
thoughts to yourself and the final one
is that if you defend yourself against
accusations of white supremacy then
actually you are hoping to preserve your
own privilege all right at the end of
this talk what I what I'd hope to do was
to talk about two more synthetic ideas
about where we are what it means and
what we might do about it the first one
is something I call cultivated
insecurity and it is the idea that many
people find themselves unable to stand
up and say what needs to be said because
of certain ways that society is
presently structured so it is true that
a tenured professor at a State College
is in a pretty secure position relative
to other places in society that might
one might find themselves on the other
hand it is also true that a small number
of things going wrong in one's
relationship with one's employer
suddenly puts a great many things in
jeopardy simultaneously so I knew this
to be the case and I was making this
argument long before what happened at
Evergreen had occurred I was making it
as an abstraction but now I've lived
through this episode and I've felt I
felt
personally so what goes wrong if you
have a problem with your employer well
it jeopardizes your mortgage it
jeopardizes your retirement it
jeopardizes your health care it
jeopardizes your ability to continue to
live in the same place that's a lot of
things to go wrong simultaneously and
the implication of this is that many
people who appear to be fairly secure in
their place in society actually have a
reasonable fear of things going suddenly
wrong and having a spectacular loss of
security and that that keeps people in
line who would otherwise stand up now my
contention is that this insecurity has
in part perhaps unconsciously been
cultivated by a political apparatus that
would prefer that we do not challenge it
and so in effect those things that keep
people relatively compliant because
they're afraid of what happens if they
stand up those things have advanced and
I think what has happened is that the
social justice movement has tapped into
that very same mechanism so the fact
that the social justice movement can
challenge a professor and cause them to
have to leave the university is a very
frightening fact for lots of people and
so what I experienced on the inside of
Evergreen was tremendous support from
people who refused to speak and I
mentioned this many times I I emailed my
colleagues about it and I said you know
we have a culture of fear on this campus
and I can't tell you how many people
have approached me privately and they've
told me they're supportive of what I'm
saying and they hope I'll keep saying it
but they're not going to say anything
themselves because they're afraid of
what will happen I can't even say that
they're wrong I mean clearly they're
right
so that culture of fear results in a
number of things a it results in
arguments that need to be made not being
made it results in those who are making
arguments that need to be made being
isolated but maybe most disastrously it
results in a completely false impression
to the outside world of
where the the preponderance of opinion
is it looks if you look at Evergreen and
you look at who says what it looks like
I was one of very few voices that
disagreed with this equity proposal
which suggests that maybe there's
something off about me on the other hand
if you were capable of listening into
the private conversations as well as the
public conversations you would
understand that evergreen was fiercely
divided over the proposals that were
advancing so it colors the narrative in
a very in a very dangerous way and it
results in what I would call an epidemic
of cowardice so we have an epidemic of
cowardice in the university system it's
a mirror for the epidemic of cowardice
that we have in our political system as
well and the important take-home lesson
is that if you want to win this game if
you want the values that probably speak
for all of us the desire to see
government that functions to see it
function to liberate people to achieve
good things and to be free of fear of
misfortune if you want those things the
way to get there is to cultivate
security for those who stand up you want
people who stand up they're going to pay
a price because those who are trying to
incentivize bad policy will ensure that
they do but if you can engineer a
mechanism that causes them to feel
there's some other kind of security they
will stand up because in general people
are are ready to say what needs to be
said unless their peril is immediate and
frankly unless it involves their
families all right now a final point as
I mentioned before I find myself in a
very odd circumstance where although
I've been on the left for my whole life
I now find that many of the people who
are most interested in talking to me are
somewhere over on the right and I've
done a lot of thinking about what this
means and what its implications are for
us and I want to give you a brief model
that I think suggests something about
where we should be headed many of you
have probably taken what's called the
political compass test
I want to be a little bit cautious about
this I cannot vouch for the political
compass test ability to place you on the
map but what I do want to defend is the
two axis model that it argues for when
looking at political questions so if you
think in your mind of an x-axis and a
y-axis on the x axis are left and right
those are political left and right on
the y axis our authoritarians on the top
and libertarians on the bottom so
libertarian here does not mean economic
libertarian it means people who favor
Liberty as perhaps the highest human
value now the reason I raised this is
because I'm ever more convinced that
left and right are not particularly
meaningful axes at this moment in
history and there's a reason for that I
find that I have very easy comfortable
conversations with libertarians on the
right in the bottom right hand quadrant
of that map I am far over in the bottom
left-hand quadrant of that map I am a
left libertarian the fact that left
libertarians and right libertarians get
along easily owes to the fact that we
have almost complete overlap in our
values if you if I as a left libertarian
ask a right libertarian how they feel
about a fair system they favor it just
as I do and the reason that they favor
it is quite clear
the reason they favor it is because a
fair system works better the more people
who have access to the market the more
people who are capable of innovating and
delivering things to the market the
better the market discovers new things
that are valuable so a crew right
libertarian favors a fair system and a
true left libertarian favors a fair
system where we differ is over policy
those on the left are traditionally a
bit over enthusiastic about meddling
with a system in order to make it better
and they tend not to appreciate the full
significance of the unintended
consequences that tend to come along
with policy those on the right tend to
be a bit overly cautious about tinkering
and so they will shoot down a proposal
that might in fact be
beneficial because they fear the
unintended consequences perhaps more
than they need to but in an era where
nobody on left or right knows what
policies we should be advocating there's
very little reason for these two
quadrants to disagree we agree on what a
good society would look like we may not
agree on how fair society is presently
and we may not agree on the wisdom of
tinkering but we agree that fairness is
a good thing and the really important
point is that we also agree that
authoritarianism is a great danger we
should be united those of us on the
libertarian left and the libertarian
right should be united against
authoritarianism in all its guises now
this actually provides a strategic
advantage if we take it seriously and
the reason that it does is that the
authoritarians on the authoritarian left
and the authoritarians on the
authoritarian right do not like each
other at all they don't get along and
they cannot team up so to win this
battle the right approach is to
recognize the natural allegiance based
in values of libertarians on the left
and libertarians on the right and to
confront the authoritarians having won
that battle the proper thing to do will
be to recognize that the solutions that
have been embraced by libertarians on
the right and libertarians on the left
are all inadequate to the problems of
the 21st century socialism isn't going
to get us out of this
libertarianism isn't going to get us out
of this we actually have to sit down
with a fresh sheet of paper and start
thinking about what kinds of solutions
are adequate to the challenges we face
we need to recognize the solutions that
were proposed in the 18th and 19th
centuries are all of them not aware of
the danger that evolution in markets and
in political structures poses to
whatever solution making you would be
tempted to engage in that on the one
hand might be a bit frightening because
it suggests that nobody has the answers
but I would submit to you it also
suggests that the possibility of a much
better
future might simply be a matter of
confronting the question with fresh eyes
thank you
we'll break for another half hour